Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Undated 1969, Miscellaneous Union Business 1969, and January 1970 to December 1970. (Reel 57)
  - No Date, 1969, 1 (Reel 57)
    Detailed letter from Rev. Claude C. Williams on his activities during the 1930s; "Resume of Work for the Union, 1960-1969" by Mitchell; Statement of the Parent Advisory Committee to the Tri-Parish Board on the firing of Sister Anne Catherine Bizalion as Director of the Vermillion Parish Headstart Program; speech by Sister Anne Catherine entitled "Experiments in By-Passing the Establishment"; NSF Draft Statement of Programs, Goals, and Structural Changes; materials relating to the formation of the Southern Mutual Help Association; 36-page handbook for plant managers outlining anti-union tactics; handwritten notes by Mitchell pertaining to the NLRB investigation of an election at Riviana Foods, Inc.; contract between Local 300 and various menhaden fishing companies at Moss Point, Mississippi; minutes of a meeting of the Local 300 Executive Board
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1969, 2 (Reel 57)
    Folder 1943 -- Weekly organizer's reports by H.L. Mitchell. Folder 1944 -- Not Filmed
  - January to March, 1970, 3 (Reel 57)
    The NLRB ordered a hearing into the union's charges of unfair labor practices during the September election at the Riviana Foods plant in Abbeville, Louisiana; see the various papers issued by the Board (Jan. 16, 21, 29; Feb 6), Mitchell's press release on the hearing (March 5), and the copies of affidavits taken in the case, including one by Sister Anne Catherine Bizalion (Jan 30; Feb 17). There is a great deal of correspondence from Roy M. Raffield on his attempt to organize fishermen's co- operatives in Florida; see also Mitchell to NSF Southern Director Leonard E. Smith on the same subject (Jan 6). A group of students from Oberlin College undertook a winter survey of sugar cane workers during January; however, the only item in the papers for these months related to their project is a sample survey form (n.d. [Jan])
  - April to June, 1970, 4 (Reel 57)
    There is a computer print-out of the survey of sugar workers conducted by a contingent of Oberlin students during January which provides a detailed statistical analysis of the workers' living conditions (April 28). A summary of the survey results appears in the testimony of Amy Gladstein and Bruce Griffiths before the USDA sugar cane wage hearings at Houma, Louisiana (June 5). The papers also include copies of the testimony by Mitchell, Sister Anne Catherine Bizalion, and Louisiana labor official Henry Pelet at the same hearings. Further information on the survey appears in the copies of letters from Amy Gladstein to Sister Anne Catherine (June 10). There is a Decision by the US Court of Appeals in the case of Local 300 v. McCulloch (June 19). The papers also include a copy of the Brief of the NLRB General Counsel in the Riviana Foods, Inc. case (April 3), a letter from Mitchell to NSF Executive Secretary Fay Bennett on racial conflict within the Southern Mutual Help Association (April 20), and a letter from Mitchell to Frank McCallister on re-organizing NSF (May 22)
  - July to September, 1970, 5 (Reel 57)
    There is a frequent exchange of correspondence during these three months between Mitchell and AMC Secretary-Treasurer Patrick Gorman on the International's participation in a campaign to unionize Louisiana sugar cane workers; see also Gorman's memorandum on his conversation with Father Vincent J. O'Connell of Lafayette, Louisiana on the same subject (July 30). The papers include a copy of the Decision of the NLRB Trial Examiner in the Riviana Foods, Inc. case (Aug. 5), as well as the Exceptions to the Decision filed by the NLRB General Counsel (Sept 4) and a letter from a Riviana plant employee (n.d. [Aug]). On the Southern Mutual Help Association, see the Outline of Objectives (July 8) and the minutes of the Committee on Farm Labor Organization (July 20)
  - October to December, 1970, 6 (Reel 57)
    On the continuing debate over the AMC role in organizing sugar cane workers, see Mitchell's exchanges with Gorman (Oct 2, 23; Nov 2, 10), an important exchange between AMC Vice-President Richard A. Twedell and Gorman (Oct 8, 15), and Mitchell's proposal for an organizing strategy (n.d. [Nov]). Several letters from lawyer James Youngdahl provide a running account of the progress of Local 300 v. McCulloch, the suit filed to test the constitutionality of excluding farm workers from the National Labor Relations Act (Oct 23, 28; Nov 9; Dec 29). There is a copy of the brief filed on behalf of three civil rights workers arrested during July, 1969 for "criminal trespass" during a meeting with sugar workers (Nov 25). Finally, there is a memorandum from Mitchell to Sister Anne Catherine Bizalion on future plans for the Southern Mutual Help Association (Nov 5).
- Undated 1970 to Miscellaneous Union Business 1970. Miscellaneous items, STFU Photographic Record. (Reel 58)
  - No Date, 1970, 1 (Reel 58)
    Draft of article by H.L. Mitchell, "America's Disinherited: A Brief History of the Nation's Farm Workers' Efforts to Form Organizations"; set of materials relating to the Southern Mutual Help Association; report on the summer student program of 1970; letter from Oberlin student Gordon Johnson to Mitchell on the survey of Louisiana sugar workers
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1970, 2 (Reel 58)
    Folder 1982 -- Not Filmed. Folder 1983 -- Weekly organizer's reports of H.L. Mitchell
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1932-1971; 3 (Reel 58)
    - STFU Papers: 1, 1971; 4 (Reel 58)
      Deposition of Harry L. Mitchell in the case of Local Union No. 300 vs. Edward B. Miller, et al and South Coast Corporation, et al. -- 69 pages -- March 10, 1971.
    - STFU Papers: 2, 5 (Reel 58)
      Two STFU Sign Manuals -- no date.
    - STFU Papers: 3, 6 (Reel 58)
      Biographical sketches of STFU leaders H.L. Mitchell, J.E. Clayton, and Arthur Churchill. Includes a 22-page autobiographical account by Mitchell and a 13-page draft of an article entitled "Early Days of the STFU", also by Mitchell.
    - STFU Papers: 4, 1939-1940; 7 (Reel 58)
      STFU Ledger Book, listing local unions and officers, 1939 and 1940.
    - STFU Papers: 5, 1947-1951; 8 (Reel 58)
      STFU Ledger Book, recording meetings held by Rev. Arthur C. Churchill in the area of Memphis, Tennessee, 1947 to 1951.
    - STFU Papers: 6, 9 (Reel 58)
      Four miscellaneous undated items, including a handwritten essay by Rev. J.E. Clayton entitled, "Liberty, Justice and Freedom"
    - Union Newspapers: 1, 1935-1937; 10 (Reel 58)
      The Sharecroppers Voice (Memphis, Tenn.), April, 1935 to September, 1937.
    - Union Newspapers: 2, 1938-1940; 11 (Reel 58)
      The STFU News (Memphis, Tenn.), April, 1938 to October-November, 1940.
    - Union Newspapers: 3, 1941-1944; 12 (Reel 58)
      The Tenant Farmer (Memphis, Tenn.), May 5, 1941 to May 14, 1942.
    - Union Newspapers: 4, 1943-1944; 13 (Reel 58)
      The Farm Worker (Memphis, Tenn.), September and November 1943; February and July, 1944.
    - Union Newspapers: 5, 1946-1952; 14 (Reel 58)
      Farm Labor News (Memphis, Tenn. and Washington, DC), March, 1946 to June, 1952.
    - Union Newspapers: 6, 1952-1953; 15 (Reel 58)
      The Union Farmer (Hammond, La.), October, 1952 to March, 1953.
    - Union Newspapers: 7, 1952-1954; 16 (Reel 58)
      The Agricultural Unionist (Washington, DC), August, 1952 to February, 1954.
    - Union Newspapers: 8, 1932-1933; 17 (Reel 58)
      The Llano Colonist (New Llano, La.), April 16, 1932 to October 14, 1933.
    - Union Newspapers: 9, 1936; 18 (Reel 58)
      Southern Farm Leader (New Orleans, La.), May to November, 1936.
    - Union Newspapers: 10, 1938; 19 (Reel 58)
      Louisiana Farmers Union News (New Orleans, La.), January 15, 1938 to March 15, 1938.
    - Union Newspapers: 11, 1938; 20 (Reel 58)
      Workers Defense League News Bulletin (NYC), February to April, 1938
  - STFU Photographic Record, 1934-1970; 21 (Reel 58)
    Approximately 150 photographs relating to the history of the union, 1934 to 1970, selected, arranged, and with captions by H.L. Mitchell.
- Selections from the Socialist Party Archives, Duke University. Selections from the Howard A. Kester Papers, 1934 to 1938. (Reel 59)
  - Selections From the Socialist Party Archives, Duke University, 1934-1946; 1 (Reel 59)
    Xerox copies of 44 items from the Socialist Party Archives, selected by H.L. Mitchell. These include primarily letters from Mitchell to Clarence Senior and other Socialist Party officials from November, 1934 to May, 1936, but there is also a copy of an undated STFU questionnaire and a synopsis of the March of Time newsreel on the union, dated August, 1936.
  - Selections from the Howard A. Kester Papers, 1934-1938; 2 (Reel 59)
    Approximately 2,000 items from the Howard A. Kester Papers relating to Kester's work with the STFU, selected and arranged by H.L. Mitchell. Major topics include the Ward H. Rodgers case, the trail of H.L. Mitchell by an STFU investigating committee in early 1935, the union's relations with the Socialist and Communist Parties, the writing of Revolt of the Sharecroppers, the beating of Howard Kester at Earle, Arkansas in January, 1936, National Sharecroppers Week, the union's relationship with Commonwealth College, and the trial of Rev. Claude Williams. Notable correspondents include William R. Amberson, Roger Baldwin, J.R. Butler, Francis A. Henson, Gardner Jackson, H.L. Mitchell, Ward H. Rodgers, Julian D. Steele, and Norman Thomas.
- Howard A. Kester Papers (continued), 1939 to 1949. (Reel 60)
  - Continuation of the Howard A. Kester Papers, 1939-1949 (Reel 60)
    There is a good deal of material on an investigation of the Delta and Providence Cooperative Farms undertaken in 1940. A fragment of an autobiographical sketch by Kester appears at the end of the papers.